[Music]
hey folks welcome back to the Dark Horse
podcast livestream our 18th this is the
question and answer portion and we are
now going to address your super chat
questions starting with the ones from
the first hour and continuing on to the
ones from this hour so if you have
burning questions feel free to enter
them so as as has been the the pattern
we will spend about a half an hour on
these from the first hour at which we
have ranked mostly just by monetary
amount not entirely did a very poor job
and they will try to answer the other
ones in the order if they come in in the
second hour but we're actually going to
start with one from last time we had a
lot of good questions last time that we
didn't get to because we were focusing
on evergreen only questions there are a
number of them I'd like to get back to
now but there was one at a particularly
high dollar level that was quite good so
we're actually was start there already
from Martin when the Beringia pnes
migrated into the americas and the ice
age ended they were effectively isolated
from the rest of humanity how long would
the isolation of the varangians
descendants up needed to continue to
lead to a new and distinct species of
Homo say however Indiana's that's a
great question which I am now going to
dodge so stealthily so my answer would
be the funny thing about humans is that
human populations function like species
in other clays and so in a sense it
doesn't take any time at all of what
you're really looking at is whether they
behave differently enough that we would
justify such a claim on the other hand
if you're asking how long would it take
for the genetic isolation to create a
barrier to mating so great that they
would be incapable of crossing it a very
long time would be the answer and we can
tell that because apparently
Neanderthals and modern humans did mate
but here's the thing here's the thing
that we're all missing in this sort of
question the answer is staring us in the
face how long does it take for a
language to become uninterpretable by a
descendant language
right and so in some sense to people who
cannot communicate with each other
because they do not share a language can
produce an offspring but they are very
unlikely to buy any honorable route and
so that is a kind of speciation
mechanism but it is below the species
level is if the population level yeah no
that's great and I've just finished that
by pointing out how many such divisions
there are among the descendants of the
varangians that a Navajo and a Qunari
person in the Andes and valdivian from
the coast of the west coast of South
America or one of the people in the
southern tip of Claire Terra Tierra del
Fuego would have almost nothing in
common they were dealing with different
problems in different places and they'd
been separated by enough time and also
distance that they would have shared
little language if any and this this
this is that so there was change over
time and these species boundaries that
we put on things you know the usual
definition of species that people have
in their heads is one of can they mate
right if if two individuals can get
together and produce viable offspring
this is the so-called biological species
concept which of course raises all sorts
of questions about one of the kinds of
species concepts you might have and
unfortunately we can spend a whole lot
of time talking about all the different
species concepts once you get into it in
evolutionary biology you see that
species is a necessary distinction to
use to talk about differences between
populations but at best the boundaries
between species are always fuzzy at at
temporal borders and sometimes at
spatial ones - yeah at first they are
but in human beings if you're incapable
of conveying the concept hey how about
dinner and a cave painting maybe you're
not gonna get anywhere and so it's
effectively a mating boundary you've got
that look in your eye I do all right I'm
going to pretend you don't thanks
Christian this word from echo over
evolutionary time does the why
some lose most of its original genes and
increase its non recombining region
what is the benefit our male mutations
more risky as in a winner-take-all or
get wiped from the gene pool before I
know you wanted to answer this let's
just clarify that the Y chromosome is is
present in male mammals but that that
that particular mode of sex
determination is a mammal specific thing
so this answer may or may not what cat
cat antics may or may not obtain across
a wider swath of evolutionary history
yep all right so what I wanted to say in
response to this one is if you think
about chromosomes and the information
they carry most of your chromosomes all
the autosomes spend an equal amount of
time in male form and female form they
find out in the zygote what they're
gonna be and then they are that thing
they're trapped for that period of time
in male or female form and they act
accordingly the Y chromosome is quite
different the Y chromosome is the only
one in which the genes know whether they
came from mom or dad and that creates a
hazard with the Y chromosome which is
that it's genes can play a different
game its genes can play against the
maternal chromosomes and in their own
interest so for example a gene that
found itself on the y chromosome and in
a zygote would know that it came from
dad and therefore might take more
resources from mom during pregnancy
especially in a species or population in
which mating was not monogamous because
they would know that the siblings that
they would be depriving of resource by
extracting more than the mother was
tempted to give would not be close
relatives they'd be 1/4 siblings rather
than 1/2 siblings so in effect the best
argument that I'm aware of is that the Y
chromosome is devoid of most coding
genes because it is untrust
and therefore it has effectively been
shut down so here's the punchline I
thought that the white chromosome being
untrustworthy was a pretty good punch
line already it gets better okay if
patriarchy were a real thing it would be
on the y chromosome and therefore it has
been shut down because the rest of the
genome understands it has an interest in
preventing that kind of competition from
breaking out now I want to be very
careful here I do not believe that
patriarchal phenomena are unknown or
impossible it is patriarchy which I
regard as a myth and so noting that
biology long before anybody was
discussing anything had taken up arms
against the possibility of patriarchy
and had left the rest of the genes in a
a rauzein veil of ignorance situation
where genes don't make rules that favor
males over females because half the time
they'll be in a female form and
therefore it wouldn't make any sense to
do it that's the situation we find
ourselves in for the most part and so it
doesn't mean history hasn't been very
unfair to females it has in some ways it
has been unfair to males in some other
ways it is time for us to renegotiate
this deal between the sexes but
understanding how deep the biology of
this conflict and how rich the solutions
to it have been over the course of
hundreds of millions of years is well
worth our consideration in navigating
that this did not start with people yeah
so I feel like both of these should
should warrant much longer conversations
and indeed I want to take slight issue
with two things that you said I'm
distracted by the fact that there's a
cat behind me in the blinds
you're gonna take issue with what I said
even though you promised to obey I did
not know you didn't know I agree with
you that especially the way that the
people who I like to call the pseudo
feminists are suggesting that patriarchy
is explaining a lot of the world is is
not right but from in terms of the word
as it is used by anthropologists
where we have these sort of three
different endings that are often
appended to matrices I to delineate
whether or not it tends to be the female
line of the male line that has in the
case of locality Metro locality versus
petrol locality do children when they
marry tend to go and live with their
mothers family or with the with the
bride's family or with the groom's
family I'm gonna forget one Oh lynnie
ality patrick petrol in eality and
Michelini allottee how do how do
resources turn to flow but especially
names and so obviously you know i didn't
take your name but in general we tend to
have a patron lineal society and then
our key refers just to power so who
tends to end up holding those are reins
of power and it almost always has men
right and there are a lot there are a
lot of understandable evolutionary
reasons for that so I would say you know
we tend to have there's a lot more
variation in whether you have major
local natural local or petrol local
societies metro lineal of petrol lineal
societies but with regard to sort of who
ends up doing the work of the world
outside of the home and therefore has
the power it does tend to be men sure
and so at that level at the sort of
anthropological definitional level of
what the term means we have we tend to
have patriarchal structures rather than
matriarchal structures but that does not
mean that you know we're living in a
top-down men have made all the rules in
order to enslave women sort of world
which was the sort of cartoon version
that we hear from the third wave of
young feminists wouldn't make sense for
men to do it and they don't do it but it
doesn't mean that men haven't come up
with some perfectly ridiculous solutions
to problems unacceptable stuff but um
but consider the possibility that
patriarchy as it is wheeled wielded in
common parlance is a myth that obscures
a much more interesting and nuanced set
of questions about the predicament that
men and women find themselves in today
so the second thing that I wanted to
take a slight issue with is the idea
that only the y chromosome is capable of
knowing where it's from and I think I
mean you you know this but the way that
you said it it sounded like there is no
ability for genes to track their
effectively there
heritage and we know you this concept of
genomic imprinting which emerged from
the David Haig Lab in the 90s I guess
but when we were in graduate school a
little bit before suggest that actually
particular genes can track who they're
who they're from and actually you know
paternal genes are more likely to
produce bigger babies the stealing
stealing taking more of mothers resource
for this baby especially in species or
in populations where you don't have pair
bonds and where the father of this baby
may not be the father of the next baby
by the same mother so the Y chromosome
is certainly only ever in in males in
mammals but there are other mechanisms
by which genes can effectively keep
track of who they came from although any
individual gene could have probably
spent equal time in men and women in its
history so let me fix what I said that
it is true that they are not the only
genes that can know but they are the
only genes in which we expect the
sequence itself to be modified by the
reliable fact of having come from the
father and so for those of you who are
finding this all mysterious
the amazing thing about the Y chromosome
is that it has one really important gene
on it
it's the sry gene or the tlg in testes
determining locus this is the thing that
tells the rest of the genome hey guess
what you're a male go down the male
pathway and so it affects what the rest
of the the genome transcribes it affects
everything else but it's basically a
signal that says go down this pathway
and the absence of that social condition
yep in the absence of that signal you go
down the other pathway which is the
default pathway which is female and so
it's not that there are no other
sequences on it but there's precious
little on the y chromosome and the
important thing is this the single locus
and so it does appear like a kind of a
sequence desert right unlike the rest of
the genome which is rich with
information of all kinds much of which
we don't yet understand this one thing
is a gene NAC
of not very interesting stuff and that's
that is in and of itself a fascinating
and conspicuous fact
all right next question is the
evolutionary process searching for
something pertaining to divergent
cognition such as high-functioning
autism or Asperger's our non-stem
analysis methods intrinsically
inadequate to engage with cognition
based analysis instead versus race or
gender
they don't totally get it new you having
a hard time parsing this one I think
there's some pieces I spot in there so
you want to go with that yeah so I don't
know whether you know what we call
high-functioning autism or Asperger's
syndrome is really a pathological state
at all right it's possible that it's
some sort of built-in low frequency
useful at a lineage level phenomenon and
then maybe the connection to
debilitating autism or severely
debilitating autism is not what it seems
because we could not afford a job of
figuring out what the ideology is and
there that work and that's that's
actually out there live among many
psychologists the idea this is not
actually a spectrum but really at least
to perhaps multiple distinct things yeah
and so anyway I guess I would say
there's a caution which is especially in
places like psychology it's not
psychologies fault initially but it is
much easier to be descriptive in the
realm of something like the mind and its
functioning than it is to be mechanistic
because Minds differ a lot even when
they work functionally in a similar way
and so anyway we end up defining
syndromes and then we discover that our
definitions create some sort of an
incompatibility when we bring them to a
logical extreme and so anyway beware
that when somebody says something like
autism they're not saying something
specific like RNAi right they're saying
something that might be at the level of
a syndrome and a syndrome might be
triggered by multiple things and
therefore have different meanings and
anyway you may be looking at something
that has a rare adaptive form that we
call Asperger's and then a pathological
form that we call autism and it's not a
spectrum at all but it has some sort of
overlap yeah and I guess the more and
look at the first brightest question the
evolutionary process is not searching
for divergent cognition per se but as we
have as we have said elsewhere in Ellis
times else when I guess humans are both
highly specialized in
I'm a generalist and we managed to be
both in part by being so social by
living in such tight-knit groups and so
having one or a few members of a group
having what you're calling your
divergent cognition in one of a variety
of ways is I mean we have talked about
before you know it might be might be
dyslexia or left handedness or or being
on the autism spectrum or any number of
things may well allow for a greater
problem solving and may actually be a
population's road into the shamanistic
when if the rest of the population is is
quite embedded than the orthodoxy yeah
I'm the sacred so I can translate that
into our usual language the evolutionary
process builds mechanisms that search so
we've called that Explorer modes and
could something like autism or left
handedness or collective consciousness
all of these things play some role and
so how the how these things interface is
a little hard to say but but somewhere
in the neighborhood of your question
seems to be a potentially right concept
well finding a cure for cancer proved to
be impossible does cancer somehow
fundamentally serve life thanks for
everything
no it doesn't serve life yes it will be
impossible to cure it it does not mean
that it will be impossible to render it
manageable so in my paper on telomeres I
believe it made the final final version
of the paper we proposed the possibility
of extending lifespans by elongating
telomeres which would only be tolerable
in the case that you were very good at
managing tumors so early that it was a
trivial matter to deal with them so
imagine for example and there's a reason
you can't do this yet and shouldn't even
dry yet but imagine that you went for
regular body scans that found a reliable
signature of something that had crossed
over into tumorigenesis and that there
was a mechanism for dealing with those
things when they were tiny and that your
scans were regular enough that nothing
ever got beyond tiny well it might be
that you could then deal with all those
cancers in a way that didn't matter to
you and you could get some extra youth
because basically you'd borrowed from
this new capacity you wouldn't want to
do anything you would want to try
anything like this right now because in
all probability proto tumors which is a
term I tried to coin in that paper which
are things that are not tumors but they
are basically one mutation shy these are
round growths that probably exist in
almost every tissue in the body on the
surface of our skin they would be moles
they would be colorful and your liver
you'd never know they were there unless
somebody went in with a microscope and
looked right but these things are likely
to be so common that if you got a scan
and you look for all sorts of growths
that were out of place you would
probably find so many of them that you'd
be overwhelmed and even if you set some
threshold where you could ignore most of
the ones that we're never going to harm
you
you would still be constantly facing
false positives where you think you had
some cancer that needed to be dealt with
and in fact what you had was some growth
that would never bother you would never
cause a pathology so we're not anywhere
near this but is it conceivable that in
the future body scans could be good
enough and techniques that using the
word surgically metaphorically here that
is surgically dealt with only that
tissue would question and didn't cause a
larger wound could be so good that we
could extend human lifespans this way
yeah that's conceivable
next question I am interested in
pursuing research in mathematical
modeling of biological systems I was
just wondering if you have anything more
to say on this there any warnings you'd
give me any trap so might easily fall
into
oh boy I mean I got to you got to hang
up to I mean I the thing that comes up
for me first is
that the few modelers that I have known
at all have not have not been focused on
hypothesis and that I don't I didn't
know them before they were modelers so I
don't know if it was drummed out of them
by by being being a modeler or if they
went into it sort of that with a
data-driven approach rather than I
bought the SIS driven approach and there
is nothing inherently about modeling
that should that can't be hypothesis
driven but that it looks at just
anecdotally to me like those being
hypothesis driven and being a modeler
aren't living particularly well
side-by-side that much the detriment of
the accuracy of the models that we're
using so you know keep hypotheses front
and center in your mind yeah predictably
enough going to have a similar message
which is models can be made to mirror
behaviors that they do not actually tell
us anything about if you include enough
parameters in the model you can get them
to spit out behaviors that look like
just about any natural thing you would
find so the utility of models is in
generating hypotheses that then require
a test in very simple cases you can use
a model to test certain ideas but as
you're dealing with something complex
like biology tends to be you want to
take a model and use it for its highest
and best use which is the generation of
possibilities which you then test in
nature and so what Heather is responding
to is that the tendency is to use models
as a cheaper way of accessing nature as
if they were true and the assumptions
just aren't supported so beware of the
problem of making models that mirror the
behavior for the wrong reasons not
because they are internally not like the
system in question and I should also say
be aware that model means really two
different things you say mathematical
model I take that to mean computer model
I'd generate models and I think they're
useful but the point is the model is a
description of the way a system might
work
and then the hypotheses get tested in
nature and if they if they give you
predictions that actually turn out to be
manifest in nature especially if those
predictions are surprising they reflect
well on the whole model so my model of
telomere senescence and cancer was
bolstered by the demonstration by human
and Grider that lab mouse telomeres were
anomalous and that wild mice had short
telomeres that prediction does have lots
of interesting implications but to me
the most important was that it reflected
well on the larger model which said
something about life history strategies
in creatures like us so two different
kinds of models what do you think is the
most accurate assessment of COBIT 19
mortality rates as best and it's very I
don't know you know I I mentioned that I
think sort of off the cuff I said that
it appears to have a case fatality rate
which mortality rate is a bit of a
looser term but a case fatality rate
being just what percentage of those
infected died something like four to
five times that of flu it could be ten
times
I think there's I don't think we will
find that it has been during this time
during the time of the pandemic anything
closer to that of the flu it may it may
come to that you know it mate within a
year from now if it's still here if it
doesn't disappear which some
coronaviruses do it may end up
equilibrating at something close to the
CFR for flu but I think it's gonna be
something right will have been something
right now around something like a half a
percent but I honestly don't put a ton
of confidence in that estimate yeah and
again I'm gonna dodge the question and
say I am suspicious that different
strains may differ and that may be
throwing us different locales may differ
that change over time will cause the
number to shift and even if change over
time did not cause the number to shift
that our understanding of the symptoms
and their meaning will cause our
treatment of it too
better so for example let's say I'm not
saying this is true not a doctor don't
know but if it was true that people with
severe respiratory SARS co2 infection
tend to present as somebody in need of a
ventilator but the ventilator makes
matters worse and we learn not to put
people on them you would expect the case
fatality rate to go down as a result of
our painfully earned knowledge and
anyway no doubt there are dozens of ways
in which we are learning how to treat
people better than we were in the early
phases of this which should drive the
CFR down so yeah well there's also this
so this is something we've talked about
and maybe deserves more time in the
regular part of a future episode
although at some point we're going to
start veering away from code of 19 and
talking more about other things this
virus seems at least capable of and
quite likely is mutating very very
quickly it is spread fast into many
different domains across many different
types of environments and we know you
know the genome has been mapped in a
number of strains and we know it's
changing fast that that put that right
next to the fact that we keep hearing
that both the tests for active infection
the antigen tests and tests for past
infection the antibody tests are wildly
variable in their accuracy that you you
know you don't you can't just say okay
this one has a 2% false positive and a
1% false negative these tests just seem
to be wildly variable so what might that
be about why is this white like it's one
thing to try to find a vaccine and we've
talked before about how difficult it may
be and how we may never get one but you
know hopefully we do but why are the
tests so bad the tests as we've talked
about right may be bad because using a
test developed for one strain will not
work on a different strain if the
evolution if the rate of evolution is so
fast and the piece of the you know
whatever it is that the test is looking
at it doesn't happen to be in the new
strain we may get mu may be getting you
wouldn't get false positives this way
but you would get a whole lot of false
negatives so if you had and likely it
would be mostly the serology tests the
tests that were antibody testing per
passed infection and that would actually
if that were true that would mean that
the background rate of infection
many parts the world was much higher
than it appears to be and that would
also you know once the denominator goes
up that means the case fatality rate
goes down but that also mean it just has
huge epidemiological implications if
it's true if a whole bunch of people who
felt like they probably were sick
actually were sick even though the tests
are coming back negative and a whole
bunch of people therefore who didn't
think they were sick probably were as
well but perhaps the tests that they're
using were made in one part of the world
of one part of the country that had had
a different strain than the one that was
in the further world they're living in
so this is a possibility that I haven't
heard anywhere else except in our house
and it's it makes this question you know
what's the most accurate assessment of
copa90 mortality rates even harder to
get close to it does and also suggests
yet again that we were at least in the
right neighborhood when we're talking
about the Theodore Roosevelt the
aircraft carrier that had an outbreak
and the lost opportunity of a population
of exactly known dimension that could
have been followed in order to figure
out how these patterns actually work so
I guess the point would be look it's
still not too late to start
carefully tracking some populations so
well that you could establish who had
had an infection you know frankly by you
know viral shedding or whatever and then
we could test the hypothesis that the
tests are you know inaccurate in an
inconsistent way based on what strain
you had versus what strain the test was
built for yeah so anyway still a good
idea and if not for this pandemic then
for the next one next question the
YouTube video mathematical challenges to
Darwin's theory of evolution is a
scholarly discussion at the mathematical
mathematical impossibility of Darwin's
theory is this a reasonable challenge
the theory is this a new idea you're
nodding as if you know the video I do I
looked it up to make sure it was the
video I was thinking of oh when you saw
the question yeah it's uh David Glanton
er David Berlinski and Stephen Meyer oh
it's that one yeah it's that one okay so
alright I'm now going to get in trouble
with
everybody so hopefully you'll stick with
me you've committed to do that and the
rest of you it was nice knowing ya but
okay I can tell you both too they will
as well and the pets I heard the animals
yeah well they don't know what you're
talking about so this won't change
anything for them
no that's true in any case I I know
those three guys and I must say I quite
like them there are challenges say who
it is against David Gartner who
triggered a wave of controversy by artis
a computer math guy and he basically
said that he had come to the point that
he didn't believe that Darwinism was a
an accurate model and of course Steven
Meyer of the Discovery Institute has
long been searching for evidence that
Darwinism is inadequate to this to
explain life as we know it and David
velinski has yet a third position none
of them have the same position which is
interesting but they're all skeptical of
the standard-issue Darwinian framework
yeah and you know when I met these guys
I told them that I thought there was
something to the challenges that were
being leveled not all of them but some
of the challenges that were being
leveled had content to them but that the
solution actually was a deeper kind of
Darwinism that basically Darwin had been
right Darwin was of course not very
specific because he couldn't be in the
absence of knowledge of how genes work
but I you know I flat out told him I
said look this is your Waterloo are you
ready for it and you know I haven't
persuaded them and they haven't
persuaded me but the thing that I find
so troubling is that the field of
legitimate evolutionary biologists
treats all of this as if it is not
offered in good faith I don't believe
this is the case in any of these in the
case of any of these three people they
are all skeptical for their own reasons
I believe they are in the end wrong but
it doesn't mean that every challenge is
incorrect and you know challenges like
you know
is there enough time given the
mechanisms that are presented in order
for the for adaptation to have
discovered the various things that we
credit to it if that is the if the
mechanisms involved are the ones that we
described in the textbook I think this
is actually a fair challenge and to the
extent that the field discovers that the
mechanisms we already have in discussion
are perfectly adequate the field will
become stronger for having demonstrated
that and to the extent that we find out
that actually there is something there
is a gap between what we claim is being
explained and the mechanism that we have
said explained it that points directly
to another mechanism now my point is
that mechanism is Darwinian it's a
different Darwinian mechanism Darwin
didn't say you know DNA to protein was
the only Darwinian mechanism he didn't
have any position on it because he
didn't know about DNA so my point would
be there is a missing mechanism it does
render the story that we tell about how
Darwinism works inadequate and that in
effect the solution involves what we
have called Explorer modes that
basically over time the route Darwinism
discovers more and more effective ways
of exploring design space and so it
finds solutions faster than it would if
it was doing this totally haphazard
thing where you know you've all heard
the story right there are lots of
mutations most of them are bad every so
often one of them is good those good
ones off and go extinct anyway yes they
get accumulated the accumulation
ultimately produces things like wings
and eyes and all of that and my point
would be now Darwinism produces those
things but it isn't that simple random
mutation mechanism it's other ways that
Darwinism has given rise to exploration
of design space and I think frankly as
much as some of the critiques offered by
Gartner and and Berlinski
and Myers are I think dead ends and not
accurate no I'm not I'm not concerned
about the Cambrian explosion for example
but
to the extent that some of their
critiques actually really do stand up to
scrutiny the field should take them
seriously these are decent people and
they're offering the produces people and
very smart people who are not who are
not naive about the level of complexity
that they're thinking about yes well I
mean look two of them are not biologists
right some of their critiques actually
are fairly easily dealt with one of them
is a biologist and a very good one right
now he does have a take he's he has a
particular thought which is that design
is the explanation and I think he will
turn out to be dead wrong but but
nonetheless the quality of the evidence
that he brings to bear is higher than
you would expect yeah so I'd like to get
through at least the 20 other questions
here so we had a lot more let's do a
little fast and go to the next
well I just lost or I was off can you
tell me how seemingly complex animal
instincts evolved that are inherited
Thanks not quickly I mean I think I
think you kind of just got there
actually with the last question yeah I
mean it's like everything else and you
know darkness does a good job with you
know as a beautiful job in fact on the
eye and how you get to an eye with the
challenge that we've all heard you know
if half an eye is of no value how could
you possibly get to an eye and it turns
out half an eye is of great value and so
being able to spot how small differences
in capacity could accumulate with no
places where there is a big jump
downward in utility that's the basic
answer and so you know a crude ability
to deploy some program in the world that
you might call an instinct that has some
tendency to adjust the probability of
finding food or whatever in your favor
that gets refined over time into
something that's almost impossible to
imagine but if you saw all the steps
you'd get it yeah and I mean I think
there's something if I don't know who
the questioner is so I don't know if
they've used the language here with with
intentional precision and you know
instinct instance is one of these words
that often animal behaviorists don't use
anymore because there's very little that
is just completely programmed in at the
level of behaviors but complex animal
instincts might actually be pointing to
something that is behaviorally simple
but actually requires a whole interplay
of anatomical physiological endocrine
illogical perhaps developmental things
to come together and so you know how do
you get a simple and perhaps binary
outcome with a whole lot of complexity
behind it and you know it's going to be
the same kind of answer but it is harder
it is harder to imagine your way there
and you know as as again Dawkins has
said failure of imagination is not an
argument but it is you know the I
argument that he makes so elegantly the
Dawkins makes so elegantly is an easier
one to to grok right
any ability to sense the difference
between light and dark is better than no
ability at all even if that first
photoreceptor if any of us who are fully
who have full vision we're to go back to
that state it would feel like a terrible
loss but from total darkness it's a
great advance so when you have a system
that looks like you pull out a single
thing and you've got a Jenga tower
falling it's harder to imagine how it
worked but but with most these systems
we can't actually live together and
that's in fact a lot of what a lot of
what to comparative anatomist and
development biologists do is figure out
what those what those are okay next
question
I love the podcast thank you both for
what you do question when you get on a
plane assuming you are a healthy say 30
is adult if your essential job required
travel assume driving is not an option
any travel advice yeah it's a it's a
good question I've seen some horror
stories from planes just packed and and
[Music]
you know for sure wear a mask and and do
everything you can to you know create
your own personal cocoon of airspace but
beyond that you know I we we were flying
a fair bit in the last couple of years
and haven't of course at all I guess
since I got back from LA is the last
time I there must flew in mid-february
no actually I'm so good three months
which is a long time for us and I you
know I miss travel I do not miss I I
dread the idea of being on a flight and
yet it is necessary for many people and
it in some ways it might be safer than
driving a you say driving isn't an
option but having to go you're having to
go on land through a lot of places that
may have their own little pockets of
epidemics having to you know pump gas
and get food and such may put you at
that high risk and you know the short of
the flight the safer probably
you know dad here that's certainly gonna
be true how much safer is unclear I mean
that the answer is you're probably safe
if you're not in the path you know and
the way these things move around planes
is not straightforward but if you're not
in the path of somebody who's sick then
you're probably safer and but here's
what I would say I'm actually facing
this question because there's a flight
that I am supposed to take it's not real
soon but soon enough few weeks and you
know I'm trying to figure out whether or
not I should cancel it or not and you
know it's for something I've already
committed to and it's the one thing that
remained on the calendar when everybody
cancelled everything else and I have
thought about the question of whether in
this case I would break out one of the
respirators that we have for no leases
or carpentry or for you know if you
spray and solvents or something like
that
so these things are much more
industrial-strength much less
comfortable than the bandanna I got to
tell you but the problem the model for
the infection when I'm running around
with in my head at the moment is there's
some vessel that when you encounter
somebody sick begins to fill and if it
gets above some threshold then you're
likely to get sick if you keep it below
that threshold you are unlikely to get
sick nothing is impossible but unlikely
so if you have a two-minute interaction
with somebody it's very very unlikely
you will reach that threshold even if
they're sick right but if you were
sitting next to somebody who's sick the
chances that you'll get through you know
an hour flight and not reach that top
level is pretty low with a you know
respirator prevent you from getting to
that level I think so I would want to
see it also depends on how many ways it
can spread you know so that the the
emerging medical consensus which who
knows if it's right but the emerging
medical consensus suggests that airborne
is clearly the way that this spreads
most and the aerosols probably and
fomites the stuff on surfaces poses
actually very very little risk which if
true you know means that retail can open
v/o things like that and it's sitting
next to someone if you and they are both
masked um is actually pretty safe
yep well if you and they are both masked
yes but I would still say in a flight
and you know even an hour flight you
could get stuck on the tarmac for an
extra hour and so you know I trust my
bandana if I'm in a position to limit my
interaction with anybody I don't know so
I'm you know blazing through a store to
you know to get groceries or whatever
I'm in a lot of control over whether I
spend a lot of time with one person and
an airplane you lose that and so I might
go the extra step and and use a
respirator though I'm not happy about
that as a choice I do think it would
work a quote from my lecturer quote the
role of an educator is to teach children
tune off the arm of social injustice for
wounded in the body of the system Wow
end quote
any tips for aspiring teachers who don't
want our society to hemorrhage out
and the schools of Education have been
captured and that means that they are
literally coming for our children how is
it that we can get you Elizabeth and
other aspiring teachers to stay in the
system and actually teach children the
right thing I think you know first you
have to get through school and that
probably does require some some feints
some some lies about what you actually
believe in that's awful that's not
education is the opposite of education
but once you have children you you don't
do that you teach them to experience
their own bodies and the physical world
and learn from what they experience and
believe their eyes before they believe
what someone told them or what they read
in a book or on the internet and you
know it depends of course what level of
educator you're looking to be if it's
five year-olds 10 year-olds 15 year-olds
20 year olds fifty year olds but
increasingly it's tough within the k-12
system to do even what you know aspiring
teachers who really have a drive to
educate want to do because of because
basically the authoritarian stuff coming
from from on high that you know come in
nice sounding boxes like No Child Left
Behind and such but are actually ways to
enforce orthodoxy on children and and
believe them of passion that was a very
promising answer no I would just say
there is no good answer I don't know how
you would get through such a program I
certainly wouldn't on the other hand
what's certain to happen is the more
absurd the claims become and the more
ubiquitous they become in school as a
result of the fact that the schools of
Ed are are selling people this nonsense
the fact is people will have no choice
but to pull their children out of those
schools and then the schools will
collapse and so I don't look forward to
that period it could be the end of us
because it might have a very destructive
effect on our body politic but but I
don't think we're very close to the end
of the of the story of this pollution
because it's gotten so abhorrent that
you know people will not tolerate it no
and you actually mentioned one of Toby
our 14 year olds teachers in the last
livestream
who created these he's both his English
and history teacher and he created a
whole section on dystopias and and it's
just doing a fantastic job he's not
pushing anything down anyone's throat
but he's exposing these children to so
many different forms of literature and
film and music that basically teach
think for yourself without saying a
piece of course it doesn't work when you
say okay I'm going to slowly early on
many thought that coronavirus had
already arrived including myself a virus
did the rounds here in Shetland late
late January which seemed to fit
apparently it was h1n1 have you seen in
the information regarding concurrent
viruses I haven't no that's and that's
fascinating that's intriguing you know
if I don't have anything more to say
about no it's probably worth looking
into them yeah
oh the next two before we skip to the
next ones are just comment someone wants
us to look at an email sent last month
Zack if you would just highlight that so
you remember to do it it's I think it
was maybe the last one in the last live
stream I'm wondering if you might have a
chance to read an email Jason Pollock
and then keep this information flow
running please Peter says we will so
Zachary if I go here yep I see it
alright our cats are getting hungry
we're running low I hope they don't
attempt to gnaw off the unjust limbs
that are failing to feed them they meet
you on each other but I think social
injustice is not
on their list all right yeah but they're
in cat suppose I think yeah flus next so
first question from the current live
stream from Gumby the Green flus
infections fertility rate is only point
zero three percent okay so I the popular
point one percent figure is for
symptomatic cases which is clearly what
I was referring to earlier but
seventy-seven percent of flu cases are
asymptomatic thus I say kovat is ten to
thirty times deadlier what's your
current estimate of Cove AIDS IFR
that's I wonder if I think you probably
asked this before we answered that
question in the last one because I think
I was certainly working with the popular
point one percent figure for flues IFR
but given that 77% of flu cases are
asymptomatic me understand flu a lot
better than we understand Kevin 19 it
wouldn't surprise me at all if seventy
seven percent or there abouts of Co but
19 cases recent Ematic so I hope really
true but I don't know I'm taking them
yeah I'm taking this at face value of
the question fact is we don't know and
the number of cases that are
asymptomatic and possibly not testing
positive means that our data are are
just lacking yeah so it could well be
that COBIT is ten to thirty times
deadlier I don't I don't think that is
in any way outside of the realm of
possibility if you have a reference on
the asymptomatic flu being that high
would you send it to support at Bret
Weinstein dotnet Thanks
if damage causes aging why does exercise
slow aging down does it increase
telomerase unless lengthened telomeres a
really good question in fact somebody
and asked me this over email today let's
just say there are several things in
play one
first of all exercise is not specific
enough and we have there are several
tissues that don't behave in a normal
way because their cellular structure is
not standard
so skeletal muscle being multinucleate
and strength training being a matter of
increased fiber density or fiber number
rather than increased cell number means
that you can in some sense build muscle
without adding cells therefore it not
degrade your quantity of remaining
telomere there's also szeliga student
redic and synaptic connections and
neurons right and yes in fact that was
exactly what I answered this person over
email was that the brain is also similar
in the sense that exercising the brain
is not a matter of cellular growth it's
a matter of dendritic growth and so that
also doesn't predict degradation through
use quite the opposite but you do see
damage from from what the numbers are
but something like going to you know 90%
and beyond
of what you're capable of doing both at
the muscular and cardiovascular levels I
think actually puts you at least for a
short term at greater risk of getting
any viruses or bacteria that you may be
exposed to and probably also does cause
faster agent of those tissues that were
damaged from that particular kind of
exercise so honest-to-goodness cellular
damage does have this effect some
tissues involved don't regenerate very
well so cartilage for example does not
regenerate and you can give yourself
arthritis by for example running on hard
surfaces this sort of thing so what I
would say is it's a tissue by tissue
analysis and then the final complexity
is that exercise obviously does some
things for you that actually reduce
where even if the exercise itself causes
wear if it brings your weight down then
the amount of wear and tear you're doing
for you step is less so it's a complex
phenomenon and what you need to do is
figure out what the net of all of these
things are and also figure out how to
play the game right so to the extent
that you know for example biking has the
cardiovascular benefits of running but
it doesn't do the damage to your joints
it may be something worth considering
it's really even more so right
hi math major here after you prove a
conjecture it becomes a theorem without
an axiom axiom is something you can't
prove and assume correct foundations of
mass otherwise absolutely correct
analogy love from Russia PS allowing
open discussion certainly wins yep I
love this now there is some ambiguity
because I mean basically these things
don't map perfect this is a reference to
our episode 1516 it would have been
right and so the I think the point that
this this person is making is that an
axiom is presumed true which is also the
case for a theory right presumed true in
the case of axiom the part that I think
I got wrong is that an axiom could turn
out to be false right and so anyway
several people did point out this nuance
the upshot wasn't entirely clear but
let's just say the mapping is not
perfect I think I suggested that it was
closer than it actually is
but nonetheless the parallel is there
the question is really one of
terminology and anyway I have to say I'm
pretty excited that a large number of
people seem to have taken the the
question of these terms and their
meaning and their philosophical
interaction very seriously which means
the message made it through so anyway
that was the point and let's keep
discussing it because we might be close
to making for a higher quality
interaction excellent sorry I was
distracted there was a cap behind you
climbing the dark arts echo says many
thanks for answering the FF Evergreen
episode was very beautiful Thank You
echo he's a two-part Joe actually said
that Alex Jones video and him moving to
Spotify was not true he's doing it
because he wants to try to model where
the platform as a partner censorship was
not actually part of the move it was in
the very same podcast with Pakman keep
up the good work so I haven't seen any
of it I don't know oh my god that's like
that's incredible
alright well first of all my apologies
to you Joe for taking Alex's
video at face value but it's almost they
were good friends right
well I didn't know if they were good
friends but it was almost hard to
imagine that that Alex Jones would have
said something so clearly false because
it couldn't possibly result in anything
other than Joe who has the biggest
megaphone on earth saying that's not
true so you know how would you do it why
would you do it but but anyway I called
it wrong so anyway I do hope that Joe's
moved to Spotify has a positive impact
on it eliminates the sensorial bias but
who knows if that was part of his
thinking
can wearing masks prevent the spread of
strains that have mild or no symptoms
this is an excellent question and I have
and I have wondered it you know given
that people who are let's just make it
clean and say who are asymptomatic are
not coughing air droplets of people at
the very least they need to be in closer
proximity probably for longer because
speaking is going to eject fewer than
coughing or sneezing well that said you
know something like like singing or
yelling will produce a lot of air
droplets and people do you know all of
us sometimes find myself talking like
and can we watch something come out of
her mouth much to our embarrassment
right so yes but will they will masks
prevent as many infections in in a
person who is asymptomatic who was
wearing them as opposed to a person who
is symptomatic was wearing them probably
not but certainly will prevent more it
will prevent more infections than not
wearing it at all yeah I guess I'm not
really sure why one would expect it not
to work I mean the fact is it's not
about maybe I just can't read it can can
wearing masks prevent well yeah I guess
you could read it that way I read it as
as you know will they do they stand some
chance of being effective and I you know
given that earliest the main symptom
that people talk about in sort of the
classic go but nineteen if there can be
such a thing for a disease that's been
around for less than a year is the
extreme and unending coughing and
coughing is going to just spray droplets
so if you don't have symptoms you're
going to be spraying droplets at speed
less so then right but the point is the
mask takes care of some large fraction
of droplets so to the extent that
asymptomatic people are spreading the
disease to people who haven't been
exposed yet it seems to me like the mask
has the same positive effect it will
still filter out some fraction of those
particles and result in the exposure
being that much less intense and
therefore that much
less likely to cause infection so if I
can try to translate this I think you're
saying that say I'm just gonna put fake
numbers on this say someone who is
actively coughing and is not wearing a
mask would infect 10 people and by
wearing a mask they can produce let's
make it easier can infect a hundred
people and by by wearing a mask we can
reduce that to 10 and and thus it's a
reduction of 90% of the infection
a person who is asymptomatic but has the
virus might only infect 10 people
because they're not spreading as much
and wearing a mask what is expected to
have exactly the same fractional effect
so in that case the person who would be
infecting 10 people is now only
infecting one and the person who would
be infecting 10 people is only affecting
10 but there still is just as much gain
in in cain't and loss there's just as
much decrease in infection transmission
but you just start out at probably very
different places yes all of that assumes
droplet size is the same for the
symptomatic in the asymptomatic the
droplet numbers right but so yeah we
don't know that there's an all else
being equal assumption there that may
well not be true yeah yeah okay how much
do you trust the bioinformatics people
in regards to figuring out what's our
scope two strains there are do you trust
my Python or our program so so should we
trust the implicit models both a general
and a particular question
yeah it's this one here
certainly I don't trust the attitude
that my Python or our program says so in
fact this is this is a big beef that I
have with a lot of the way that modern
that the analysis part of modern science
is done that even very careful
scientists who are hypothesis driven and
went to great lengths to do exactly the
right experiment in order to address to
distinguish prophesies and collected
data very carefully in in a very
controlled way are often very willing to
throw those data into some effectively
big complex black box of a statistical
analysis program and have something pop
out the other side I'm going to pop what
pops out is something I like they go oh
yeah this is wonderful and maybe don't
question whether or not they met the
assumptions of the test whether or not
they slid something wrong it's been a
long time since I've used are at this
point and I was never very very good
with it but it's it's a it's a complex
program as all you know as Sasa's as
spss is like as all of the stats
programs are and you can do too much
without really knowing what you're doing
and they let you they let you break the
assumptions of the underlying
statistical tests so this is a this is a
slightly different question since
bioinformatics and but it's also a
question about how many strains there
are and so I don't know and just as to
deciding whether some creature is a
member of a different species or the
same species is something in which we
just have a standard there's certainly
going to be a standard for strain
there's the caveat that we have said
several times which is that there are
certain to be a huge number of strains
that are never detected because they're
so quickly dead ended and so when we say
is there another strain what we're
really saying is have some strains
succeeded enough that we see it so I
don't even think the question you know
not your question but I don't think the
question how many strains are there is a
good question I don't think it's an
answerable questions how many strains
are successful enough that we need to
worry about in this distinct
evolutionary phenomena that might be a
good question
and do I trust I mean the problem is
phylogenetically speaking which is the
deep history the history of relatedness
of critters whatever they are I do trust
those models to the extent that they
minimize the assumptions right so this
is gonna throw a lot of handle but the
tradition that we come from is one of
parsimony and a distrust maximum
likelihood not that maximum likely that
doesn't actually work but the problem is
maximum likelihood introduces
assumptions about relatedness that are
certainly going to be sometimes true but
everything specifically rejects Bayesian
analysis within phylogenetic inference
right so anyway if you take a narrow a
strict parsimony approach then there's
almost nothing that can be wrong with
phylogenetic systematics other than
maybe the assumption of bifurcation but
in case of these viruses probably
bifurcation is a fair assumption
bifurcation just meaning that one one
population turns into two rather than
one population so I will tell you so it
turns into three yeah you don't the
assumption is that you don't have
trifurcation tried rotating evolutionary
events you have five occasions although
actually now that I think about it
there's no reason that a virus couldn't
infect a virus might person and I mean
you know other creatures do this too
there are certainly ways that you can
get a poly tell me which is one of these
multiple things springing from the same
node and I'm boring the crap out of most
people but we're just getting interested
right but anyway the point is
painting with a broad brush the
assumptions about phylogenetic
systematics and the model that it uses
is so dead simple there's almost nothing
that can be wrong with it other than
some pattern that doesn't fit you know
if you have two branches of the
evolutionary tree that then come back
together
then that's not going to be mapped on to
a program that assumes bifurcation right
so that sort of thing can up end it but
in general if we're trying to figure out
how many strains of the virus there are
it's not a complex question and so you
don't have a highly complex mathematical
model that can offend you you have a
very simple mathematical model and what
you're doing is shoving lots of data at
it and the more data you have the more
it drowns out the noise and the better
you can see so that's all pretty secure
so anyway that's to make a long story
short I think there is a reason to trust
some sort of broad brush analysis that
doesn't get out over its keys about how
many strains there are but how many
strains there are doesn't mean how many
strains there are it means how many
strains are we seeing actively spreading
over an hour okay um let's just at least
let's get through two more and again
we're missing so many which we apologize
thank you again for treading water
publicly you both are doing so
swimmingly like the plumber on earth
Eric seems to publicly disagree with the
viability of a game B solution however
doesn't a desirable alignment alignment
in game a suffer from hype rigidity with
respect to stability
Cyril alignment
[Music]
disability I don't know if the alignment
refers to people or ideas amateur I mean
look
certainly Eric would agree with the
fragility of the system and that some
evolution like force has made that
fragility all the more collaborative
dangers we have almost hyper fertility
I'm sure he would agree painting with a
broad brush
does he really disagree with the idea of
the possibility of a game be solution I
don't know maybe that's something he and
I ain't well he's talked I listened to a
bit of his talks with daniel
trachtenberg er yep and that you know he
I haven't listened to all of them but I
think I'm more familiar with Daniels
position than I am with Erik's objection
to it and Erik basically starts by
saying you know calling me suspicious or
not suspicious color me skeptical but
I'm listening I just I don't I don't see
that people can get their yeah which now
I mean look there are several questions
tied up here and we don't have time to
go into all of them one is is there a
system that could be reached if we could
teleport rather than figure out how to
get there is there a system that would
be stable and have the characteristics
that we would agree a game B solution
would have to have in order to be called
that that's a different question than
can we get there from here which might
be impossible even if the place to go
actually does exist and so which of
these things Erik is skeptical about my
guess would be that you know if he says
he doesn't trust that people can get
there that's a navigation question it's
not a is there an evolutionarily stable
strategy that would accomplish the goal
so I am also skeptical that that we will
get there I think it's plausible I think
it's worth pursuing until we know it's
impossible because otherwise I don't
know what we're gonna do and Erik's
solution of let's get off planet Earth
is frankly not very helpful could I'm
not sure I know what this next question
is we may go to another one but we'll
read it could the missing mechanisms be
a kind of Kaymer ISM where two organisms
come together to form a new organism
with a new unique ability that could be
one element we've talked before about
the fact that hybrids appear to be more
common than we tend to imagine which is
something that I've actually seen in the
wild where I've had animals in hand that
don't key out to one species or the
other but there will be many mechanisms
that free evolutionary exploration from
the constraints that would come from a
simple waiting around for random
mutations to change proteins enough to
alter morphology in order to get to some
new way of doing stuff
that's the simple fact and you know as
chimerism one of them well I know of one
instance of chimeras in biology that
solve a major evolutionary obstacle you
know what I'm thinking yeah yeah they're
so cute
Kerrigan monkeys and that's known to
most people as marmosets and tamarins -
oh it's an American just barely up into
Central America cute little guys yeah
cute little guys so anyway they are
obligate twin bearing and they also have
offspring that require a tremendous
amount of care and they have a difficult
nature tiny and their offspring are big
proportion of their body size so mom is
a hard time carrying them as vera boreal
and all this so anyway they're one of a
few species in which we see something
like polyandry which is multiple males
and anyway for a long time I thought it
must be that they were identical twins
which would solve the question of why
the male's put up with the two male
mates of the mother that the three of
them going around co-parenting that the
two fathers were identical twins as well
right which I you know in I almost
failed out of graduate school on this
basis because I knew they were behaving
like identical twins and yet the
evidence said that they were not
identical twins and that just didn't fit
so I basically kept making that point
that they really have to be identical
twins and the professor is all of whom
in this case were actually really
excellent just kept saying to you yes
but it's not true
right but is it true no it's not true
okay but anyway it turned out years
later that chimerism solves the problem
that I thought that identical twins
would solve in a way that I didn't think
to predict because basically in the womb
males exchange tissue and so you've got
brothers who are not one individual or
another each brother is a composite of
the same two genomes and therefore when
one brother reproduces they are passing
on the genes that they both carry so
it's really actually be that if if
brother a has sex with their shared mate
it may actually be brother B is genome
that he spreads through his sperm and I
read I'm realizing in this moment saying
there is no brother a and brother B
they're both a and B asleep
individual yes something like identical
right but I mean there's still
individuals right I mean there's still
individuals that you can look at and yes
genetically they are not genomically
individuals right but they mean you can
you can look at them and say okay that's
you know that's Steve over there yeah
you could put collar on one of them and
yeah there's something even if even if
this guy wandered off for two weeks
during her fertile period and this is
the only one having sex with their mate
that the guy who had wandered off may
actually turn out to be genetically the
father of the resulting offspring
because of the Kaymer ISM well I still
think you can't even say he may be the
father because what is he and my point
would be actually it's a very Clintonian
thing you just said digging it okay I do
want to just quickly one more question
before we stop what are your recommended
books or sites for the curious layperson
that align with your views on gender
your comments patriarchy is a myth for
example piques my interest I do not want
to be misled so this I would love to
talk about as well for a long long time
I don't know of anything that does a
beautiful job of this you know there's a
chapter in our book which won't be up
for a year ish on sex and gender mother
nature by Sarah blacker her tea is
extraordinary I've mentioned it on this
on this live stream before a little bit
my piece called on toxic femininity
which was published in Colette's
a year and a half or two years ago gets
gets at some of this our segment on kill
rose oh yeah gasps yeah which whatever
organ we are both on we talked about it
but in terms of
in terms of other books that are out
there sarah black for her DS is the one
it's called mother nature that comes to
mind and then I mean I know there others
probably probably Bobby Lowe's book sex
matters these are all you know books
that don't focus on humans so much I
don't know if you know Lord Bette sig
has any books out but I can sort of name
some of the names Barbara Smuts on
baboons there's a straw sermon every
straw Oh Beverly strassman who worked on
the Dogon people in Africa so there are
a lot of terrific biologists and
anthropologists who are looking at sex
and sex roles and what is you know what
it's called sex well in other species we
call gender in humans it's the same
thing it's the behavioral manifestation
of sex well so there's a whole lot of
interesting stuff out there and if you
know maybe we will continue to address
that I certainly hope so
mm-hmm all right all right well this has
been excellent as usual I will ask you
please if you have not already subscribe
to the channel like the video pass it
around and let us know what you think in
the comments we will see you on Saturday
at 12:30 Pacific in the meantime be well
everyone
you